Arafat Hassan

hassanarafat@yahoo.com

linkedin.com/in/arafat-hassan-3364b2146

http://www.arafathassan.github.io

Summary

Earned a Bachelor of Science (BS) focused in Geographic Information Science and a minor focusing in City and Regional Planning from The Ohio State University. Skilled in managing databases and using GIS related softwares such as ESRI ArcGIS, ERDAS Imagine, QGIS. Learned/learning programming languages such as JAVA, HTML, and Python. Experienced in Microsoft Office (Excel, Word, Powerpoint, etc.), retail, and customer service.

Experience

Systems Analyst/GIS II

City of Westerville

Feb 2022 - Present (8 months +)

- Develop short and long-range plans, goals, objectives and priorities to improve operational efficiency and effectiveness for GIS development and integrations to the best advantage of staff and constituents
- Communicate with GIS users to determine needs assessments (equipment, software, hardware, etc) to determine current and future needs and provide recommendations
- Develop and provide GIS standards, training and guidance for GIS users within the City
- Develop, administer, and maintain GIS web sites and applications for the Internet and Intranet and performs continuous updates of core City GIS data and web site information
- Communicate with the various general public, vendors, management and contractors in order to coordinate and administer the use of GIS projects and data
- Represent the GIS team on committees and task forces by serving as a technical advisor in the exchange of information or in addressing specific needs
- Prepare, process, and review written documents pertaining to GIS to ensure compliance with departmental policies and procedures
- Track time-sensitive projects and assignments to ensure timely completion
- Coordinate and oversee various special projects and/or graphics for presentations in support of the GIS system
- Establish and maintain effective working relationships with superiors, fellow workers, and vendor's representatives; ability to communicate effectively, both verbally and in writing, with same
- Assist with development of multi-year budget
- Remain current on job specific knowledge by attending training courses and professional organizational meetings and reading job-related professional journals/publications
- Review programs, white-papers, research papers, etc. to develop innovative approaches to problem solving and program evaluations, and to make recommendations
- Maintain and monitor GIS servers including performing updates

Misource GIS Technician

NiSource

Jan 2021 - Feb 2022 (1 year 2 months)

- Analyze design capital project completion information by reviewing proper pressure tests, materials, and facilities to assure compliance with proposed engineering designs, company policies, practices, standards and other applicable codes
- Update/maintain GIS and work management system to accurately reflect gas system updates using given project as-built and related documentations
- Execute capital projects including providing new gas service to new customers, public roadway improvements and relocations, gas system improvement and maintenance in a timely manner that adheres with the department metrics
- Provide technical assistance and build strong relationship through communication and collaboration with Field Engineering, Construction, M&R, and Field Operation staff
- Proactively collaborate with leaders, co-workers, and key business partners with planning group goals, objectives, and priorities to exceed department metrics
- Assist co-workers with executing their capital projects
- Guide Field Operation staff to provide accurate information for non-capital work to capital work
- Actively reaching out to participate on upcoming department projects such as beta testing migration from ArcMap to ArcGIS Pro and accurately mapping customer service lines
- Continuously learning about upcoming GIS news and tools to keep up with the industry standards and expand personal knowledge



🔰 GIS Analyst/Engineering Technician I

City of Canton, Ohio

May 2019 - Jan 2021 (1 year 9 months)

- Maintain and update enterprise GIS databases with new/existing water distribution system data in a Geometric Network
- Perform quality assurance for the water distribution system data from multiple sources (field workers, historical records, engineering drawing, and AutoCAD drawings)
- Initiator of the organizational system that keeps records of the waterline projects including creating As-Builts drawings and end of the year cost reports
- Utilization of ArcGIS Pro to append data between databases
- Apply hosted feature layers in ArcGIS Pro to append next day assignments in Workforce for ArcGIS of water assets verification for interns
- Generates custom feature layers in ArcGIS Pro through digitizing to then be published as a web layer in ArcGIS Online for future presentations
- Creates web maps and applications such as dashboards by utilizing ArcGIS Online
- Utilization of Workforce for ArcGIS, Collector, and Survey123 app to perform GPS data collection
- Performs in field data collection of GPS data from new/replaced water valves, fire hydrants, curb stops, and fittings using Trimble products
- Collaborates with supervisors to plan current or next GIS project/agenda
- Provides teaching and mentorship to GIS interns
- Assists with tech support to field workers and help fix troubleshoots with the county GIS Department



GIS Planner Intern

Delaware County, Ohio

Sep 2018 - Apr 2019 (8 months)

Assisted with converting and modifying county shapefiles from ArcView 3.2 to ArcMap 10.6 using "Import from ArcView" ArcMap extension.

Store texts/annotations including road names in a geodatabase with correct fonts and its size.

Match queries, map symbols, shapefile names, legends, title, scale bar, neatlines, north arrow in ArcMap with ArcView.

Combined converted map with updated geodatabase text annotations to export it to a PDF file.

Collaborated with supervisors to update and maintain the county maps such as new zoning, removing silvers or gaps of polygons.

Retail Sales Consultant

Sprint

Dec 2017 - Apr 2019 (1 year 5 months)

- Assisted customers with their cellular needs through creating bundles that works for them.
- Exceeded key performance objectives, including sales and customer satisfaction goals

Team Member

ZAGG, Inc.

Jun 2016 - Dec 2017 (1 year 7 months)

- Collaborated with supervisors and coworkers to train new employees
- Managed store opening or closing operations, including auditing cash register and counting inventory

COLLMBUS Barista

Columbus State Community College

Jan 2015 - Jun 2016 (1 year 6 months)

Served customers with coffee drinks in a timely manner

Managed store opening or closing operations

Server Assistant

Cameron Mitchell Restaurants

May 2014 - Jun 2016 (2 years 2 months)

Assisted servers with tasks such as delivering food to serve guests better

Organized tables in an appealing way by ensuring utensils, glasses are clean for next service

Service Champ

Taco Bell

Jun 2011 - Sep 2014 (3 years 4 months)

Implemented a plan to serve the customers in a timelier manner at drive thru

Trained new employees and supported existing employees with their tasks

CSLPIasma Reception Technician

CSL Plasma

Jul 2013 - Nov 2013 (5 months)

Assisted qualified donors in completing the screening process

Educated new donors on the use of therapeutic products made from donated plasma

Education

1 The Ohio State University

Geographic Information Science and Cartography, City and Regional Planning, Geographic Information Science, City and Regional Planning 2016 - 2018

columbus State Community College

Associate of Science - AS, General Studies 2013 - 2016

Licenses & Certifications

esri ArcGIS Enterprise: Configuring a Base Deployment - Esri

50158813

Skills

ArcGIS Products • HTML • Python (Programming Language) • Databases • Global Positioning System (GPS) • Microsoft SQL Server • Java • Microsoft Office • Cartography • Geometric Network for Utilities